莫扎特
Mozart!
莫扎特  请原谅我!
Forgive your assassin!
我承认我杀了你!
I confess, I killed you!
我真的杀了你
Si, I killed you, Mozart.
请原谅我  莫扎特!
Mozart, piet? Forgive your assassin!
原谅我  莫扎特!
Forgive me, Mozart!
先生  请开门  乖一点!
Signore Salieri, open the door, be good now!
我们有你最喜欢的东西 你将去爱的东西
Signore, we have something special for you.Something you're going to love.
啊!  真好吃!
Mmm! Is that good!
先生  请相信我
Signore, believe me.
这是我所吃过最好吃的东西
this is the most delicious thing I ever ate in my life!
真的  你错过了这些食物的话
Really, you don't know what you're miss
好了!  吵够了吧!  别闹了  先生  开门吧!
All right, that's enough! Open the door.
先生  如果你不开门的话
Signore, if you don't open this door...
我们会把食物都吃光一点也不剩给你
we're gonna leave nothing for you.
而且再也不来看你了
And I'm never gonna come see you again!
『莫扎特传』
早安!  神父
Good morning, Father.
哈里·萨列里?
Herr Salieri?
别吵我
Leave me alone.
我不能丢下孤独的老人
I cannot leave alone a soul in pain.
你知道我是谁吗?
Do you know who I am?
这有何差别?
That makes no difference.
在上帝的眼中众生都是平等的
All men are equal in God's eyes.
是吗?
Are they?
向我忏悔吧!
Offer me your confession.
我能请求上帝宽恕你
I can offer you God's forgiveness.
你练习音乐多久了?
How well are you trained in music?
我懂一些皮毛  我年轻的时候学过
I know a little. I studied it in my youth.
在那里学的?  在维也纳
-Where? -Here in Vienna.
那你一定听过这首
Oh! Then you must know this.
我好像没有听过
I can't say that I do.
那是什么?
What is it?
是当时很受欢迎的曲子
It was a very popular tune in its day.
我写的
I wrote it.
如何?
Here, how about this?
每当我们弹起它  全场都为之倾倒
This one brought down the house when we played it.
很不错?
Well?
对不起  这首也不是很熟悉
I regret it is not too familiar.
你没听过我任何一首曲子吗?
Can you recall no melody of mine?
我本来是全欧洲最著名的大作曲家
I was the most famous composer in Europe.
我一个人写了四十首歌剧
I wrote 40 operas alone.
这一首如何?
Here! What about this one?
我听过那首  那真迷人
Yes, I know that! That's charming!
对不起  我不知道这是你写的
I'm sorry, I didn't know you wrote that.
这首不是我写的
I didn't.
那是莫扎特所作的沃夫冈
That was Mozart. Wolfgang...
阿玛迪斯·莫扎特
Amadeus Mozart.
就是你责怪自己谋杀的人?
The man you accuse yourself of killing.
你听说了吗?
You've heard that?
是真的吗?
Is it true?
看在上帝的面子上  我的子民
For God's sake, my son...
如果你想忏悔...就说出来吧!
if you have something to confess, do it now.
如此才会心境平和
Give yourself some peace.
他...是我的偶像
He...was my idol.
莫扎特
Mozart.
我可以想到当时他的名字随时随地在我心中响起
I can't think of a time when I didn't know his name.
我仍在玩游戏的时候
I was playing games...
他已在国王面前演奏  包括帝王
when he was playing music for kings and emperors.
甚至在罗马教宗之前
Even the pope in Rome.
当我听到有关他的事迹时
I admit, I was jealous...
我承认我心中非常嫉妒
when I heard the tales they told about him.
他有着很好的家世
Not of the brilliant little prodigy...
他父亲甚至教他一切
but of his father, who had taught him everything.
我父亲  他甚至不关心音乐
My father, he did not care for music.
当我告诉他
When I told him...
我多么渴望成为像莫扎特那样
how I wished I could be like Mozart...
他说了!  喂!  你为什么想当只训练过的猴子
he would say, "Why? Do you want to be a trained monkey?
让我带你到全欧洲玩把戏?  像马戏团表演那样?
You'd like me to drag you around, doing tricks like a circus freak?"
我怎样才能让他知道
How could I tell him...
音乐在我心中的地位
what music meant to me?
当我父亲热切祈祷上帝
While my father prayed earnestly to God...
祈祷生意兴隆时
to protect commerce...
而我在偷偷想着
I would offer up...secretly...
希望能有那种境遇
the proudest prayer a boy could think of.
主呀!  让我成为伟大的音乐家
Lord, make me a great composer.
让我透过音乐赞扬你的荣耀  并因此显扬自己
Let me celebrate your glory through music...and be celebrated myself.
使我扬名于世界  亲爱的上帝
Make me famous through the world. deer God.
使我永垂不朽
Make me immortal.
当我死后
After I die...
让人们满心喜爱地称赞我的作品
let people speak my name with love for what I wrote.
为回报你  我将献出我的贞洁
In return...I will give you my chastity...
我的努力  我的谦卑
my industry...
及人性最祟高的品格  在我一生中的每一时刻
my deepest humility, every hour of my life.
你知道发生什么事吗?
And do you know what happened?
奇迹发生了!
A miracle!
我的生命永远的改变了
My life changed forever.
当然这都是上帝安排的
I knew God had arranged it all.
很明显  一分钟前  我还是个受挫的小孩
That was obvious. One minute I was a frustrated boy...
在一个鲜为人知的小镇 一分钟后我却在此
in an obscure little town. The next I was here...
维也纳  音乐之城
in Vienna, city of musicians...
一位爱好音乐的君王  约瑟夫  可称为音乐的国王
and Emperor Joseph, the musical king.
几年后  我就成了他的宫廷作曲师  很不可思议吧?
In a few years, I was his court composer. Isn't that incredible?
每一晚  我坐在奥皇身旁与他一起弹琴并校正皇家乐谱
Every night I sat with the emperor of Austria...playing duets with him...correcting the royal sight-reading.
事实上那人一点也不了解音乐
Actually, the man had no ear at all.
可是有一点很重要
But what did it matter?
他很欣赏我的音乐
He adored my music.
告诉我...
Tell me....
假如你是我的话...
If you had been me...
你会不会觉得上帝已经答应你了?
wouldn't you have thought God had accepted your vow?
相信我  我觉得很光荣
And believe me, I honored it.
我是贞洁的典范
I was a model of virtue.
我从不接触女人
I kept my hands off women.
我每天工作好几小时  免费教导学生
I worked hours every day teaching students, many for free!
每天开不完的会议  帮助可怜的音乐家
Sitting on endless committees to help poor musicians.
工作当时就是我的全部
Work, that was all my life.
那真是太棒了
And it was wonderful.
大家都喜欢我
Everybody liked me.
我也喜欢我自己
I liked myself.
直到他出现
Until he came.
他来到维也纳演奏自己的音乐
He came to Vienna to play some of his music...
他当时是沙兹堡主教的门客
at the residence of the Prince Archbishop of Salzburg.
我立刻去那里找他
Eagerly, I went there to seek him out.
那一个晚上
That night...
改变了我的一生
changed my life.
我穿过宴客厅的时候
As I wandered through the salon...
我开始和自己玩一个游戏
I played a little game with myself.
这个男人四岁的时候写出第一首协奏曲
This man had written his first concerto at the age of 4...
七岁的时候写出第一首交响曲  十二岁时写出第一出歌剧
his first symphony at 7, a full-scale opera at 12!
这种才华是很明显的吗?
Did it show?
是不是写在脸上的?
Is talent like that...written on the face?
他到底是哪一个人呢?
Which one of them...
他会不会是...
could he be?
莫扎特不在这里
Mozart is not here.
-别闹了  -我没闹
-Stop it! -I am.
-住手  别闹了  -我住手了
-Stop it! -I am stopping it.
我住手了  慢慢的  看到了没有?  我住手了
I am! I'm stopping it. Slowly. There. You see? I've stopped.
-现在我们又要开始了  -不要
-Now we're going back. -No!
你不知道你身在何处
Yes! You don't know where you are.
这里一切都是本末倒置的
Here, everything goes backwards.
人们倒着走倒着跳舞  倒着唱歌  甚至倒着说话
People walk and dance and sing and even talk backwards.
-这真是太愚蠢了  为什么?  -人们倒着放屁
-That's stupid. -Why? People fart backwards.
你说  我生病了
Ssa-ym-ssik!
是的  你是病得很严重
Yes, you are. You are very sick.
不  倒过来说
No! Say it backwards, shitwit!
重..
Ssa-ym-ssik.
严..
Ssik, kiss.
很..得..病..重严很得病(音同亲我屁股)
Ym...my...Ssa.
亲我的屁股
Kiss my ass.
-我才不玩这个游戏!  -快说  这是很严肃的
-I'm not playing this game! -Say it, it's serious.
这是很严肃的
It's very serious.
说  我给嫁
Marry me.
嫁...嫁给我
I'm not gonna marry you. You're a fiend.
我才不要嫁给你呢  你是个魔鬼
Uoy-evol-l-tub.
你爱我是可
Tub.
你..爱..我..
But I...
是..可..
love....
可是我爱你
But I love you?
便大的我吃什么?
Tihs-ym-tae. WO What?
便..大..
Tihs-ym-tae.
的..我..吃..
-Eat. -Eat.
吃我的大便
-Ym, my. -My.
你这只肮脏的猪
Tihs. Eat my shit.
你这个肮脏...
You filthy fiend!
-你这个肮脏!  -嘘...
-You filthy! -Shh....
我的音乐
My music.
他们没有我就开始了
They've started without me.
那就是莫扎特
That was Mozart!
当我面前打滚嘻戏的小丑
That giggling, dirty creature I'd just seen crawling on the floor.
我觉得演奏会进行得很顺利没错
-I think that went well, don't you? -Indeed.
维也纳人就是会欣赏优美的音乐
The Viennese know good music, don't you think?
当然
Certainly.
尊敬的陛下
Your Grace.
莫扎特
Ah, Mozart.
-为什么?  -什么为什么  陛下?
-Why? -Why what, sir?
为什么我要在我的宾客面前
Why do I have to be humiliated in front of my guests...
受仆人的羞辱?
by one of my own servants?
你真是太得寸进尺了
The more license I allow you, the more you take.
如果陛下不喜欢我 你可以请我离开
If His Grace is not satisfied, he can dismiss me.
我希望你能立刻回沙德堡
I wish you to return immediately to Salzburg.
-你父亲在那里耐心的等你  -不  陛下!
-Your father is waiting for you there Patiently. -No, Your Grace!
我将更喜欢您解雇我  很明显的我未能使你满意
I would prefer you dismissed me. It's obvious I don't satisfy.
我并不打算请你离开  你还是要当我的仆人
I have no intention of dismissing you. You will remain in my service...
同时学点规矩
and learn your place.
在乐谱上看来一点也不起眼
On the page it looked....Nothing!
非常简单的前奏  几乎有点可笑
The beginning simple, almost comic.
只有一个节拍  低音管  低音号
Just a pulse.Bassoons, basset horns...
好像生锈的铁盒子一样
like a rusty squeezebox.
然后  突然间
And then, suddenly...
出现高音的双簧管
high above it...
一根双簧管
an oboe.
一个音符不变地飘浮着
A single note, hanging there, unwavering.
直到黑管接手
Until...a clarinet took it over...
甜美的调子  充满了欢欣
sweetened it into a phrase of such delight.
这可不是马戏团猴子所能作的乐曲
This was no composition by a performing monkey.
是我未曾听过的音乐
This was a music I had never heard.
充满了无法满足的情感
Filled with such longing, such unfulfillable longing.
就如同听到上帝的声音一般
It seemed to me I was hearing the voice of God.
对不起!
Excuse me.
为什么?
But why?
为什么上帝却选了一个年幼无知的小孩作为他声音的工具呢?
Why would God choose an obscene child to be his instrument?
我绝对不相信
It was not to be believed.
这个地方曾经有过意外  一定是
This piece had to be an accident. It had to be.
好多了
It better be.
这个莫扎特有多好?
How good is he, this Mozart?
他真是完美极了  陛下  我上个月听过他相当杰出的歌剧
He's remarkable, Majesty. I heard an extraordinary opera of his last month.
-《克里特王》那出歌剧-那真的是最平凡的作品
-Idomeneo, King of Crete.  That?
一个无聊的作品 我也听过
A tiresome piece. I heard it too.
无聊?
Tiresome?
一个年轻人不自量力
A young man trying to impress beyond his abilities.
太多加料  太多音符
Too much spice. Too many notes.
陛下  那是我近年听到最好作品
Majesty...it was the most promising work I've heard in years.
那我们应努力将他争取过来
Then, we should make some effort to acquire him.
维也纳可以用个好德国作曲家吧
We could use a good German composer in Vienna, surely?
只要价码合理  我相信他会有兴趣的
I'm sure he could be tempted with the right offer. Say...
-为了我们的国家歌剧院  做一曲德文的歌剧
an opera in German for our National Theater.
太好了  陛下
Excellent, sire!
但陛下  不要德文好不好
But not German. I beg, Your Majesty.
意大利文才是得体的歌剧语言
Italian is the proper language for opera.
受过教育的人都会同意这一点
All educated people agree on that.
你认为如何?  内廷大臣?
Mm-hm. What do you think, chamberlain?
我认为是该有本国语言歌剧的时候了
In my opinion, it's time we had a piece in our own language.
让老百姓听德文吧!
Plain German for plain people.
卡普麦斯特(宫庭乐团团长)你呢?
Kapellmeister?
我同意剧场监督的看法
Majesty...I must agree with Herr Direttore.
德文...太粗野了  不适合歌剧
German is...scusate...too brute for singing.
宫庭作曲家  你认为呢?
Court composer...what do you think?
我认为将莫扎特请来维也纳是很有趣的构想
I think it's an interesting notion to keep Mozart in Vienna.
这会使得大主教非常的愤怒也许这是陛下的企图
It should infuriate the archbishop...if that is Your Majesty's intention.
你说对了  宫庭作曲家
You are cattivo, court composer.
我要见见这年轻人  安排一愉快的欢迎仪式给他
I want to meet this young man. Arrange a pleasant welcome for him.
好了  就这么办
Well, there it is!
感谢你  上帝
Grazie, signore.
这顶假发太适合你了  看起来实在太棒了
This is a beautiful wig for you. It looks so marvelous and I love it.
另一顶
The other one.
我想你会喜欢这一顶
Here is the other one. I think you will love it.
-你喜欢吗?  -他们都太美了
-How do you like it? -They're all so beautiful!
我三顶全要我为什么没有三个头?
Why don't I have three heads?
那很有趣 三个头
This is funny! Three heads!
-早安陛下  -早安
Good morning.  Morning, Your Majesty.
今天为我准备了什么?
What do you have for me today?
陛下  莫扎特先生  他怎么样
-Your Majesty, Herr Mozart.  Yes, what about him?
-他已经来了
He's here.
-就这样子了  很好
Well, there it is. Good!
陛下  我希望你不会认为不妥  我写了一个短曲欢迎他
I hope you won't find it improper, but I've written a march in his honor.
想得真周到  我能看看吗?
What a charming idea, court composer. May I see?
只是个小曲罢了
Just a....Just a trifle, of course.
我能试试吗?
May I try it?
我的荣幸
Majesty!
我们来开心一下
Let's have some fun.
太棒了  宫庭作曲家!
Delightful, court composer!
他进来时我能演奏吗?
May I play it when he comes in?
-悉听尊便  先生!  -带莫扎特来  但..慢慢的
-You do me too much honor. -Bring in Herr Mozart. But slowly.
我要给他惊喜
I need a minute to practice.
很好  先生!  继续
Good, continue.
很好  继续
G, Majesty.
太完美了
Excellent!
-非常棒  陛下
Very good, Majesty.
快! 向上
Tempo! Up.
轻轻然后强烈!  它他是进行曲  陛下  重复
Lightly, then strongly! It's a march, Majesty. Again.
喝彩声  陛下!
Bravo, Majesty!
先生们  请不要如此热情  谢谢
Gentlemen, please. A little less enthusiasm, I beg you.
-莫扎特-陛下
-Mozart. -Majesty.
不  我可不是教宗
No, please. It's not a holy relic.
我们以前曾经见过面...就在这个大房间里面
You know, we have met before. In this very room.
也许你不记得  你当时只有六岁  就已经演奏了最棒的协奏曲
You don't recall. You were only 6. He was giving a delightful concert!
他从椅子爬下来时还滑了一跤
As he got off the stool, he fell.
我的妹妹安东尼扶他起来  你们知他怎么了?
My sister Antoinette helped him up. Know what he did?
他抱住她  然后说：你愿意嫁给我吗?
He jumped into her arms and said, "Will you marry me? Yes or no?"
你一定认识各位先生吧!  范史威登公爵
You know all these gentlemen. The Baron Van Swieten.
-年轻人  我相当喜欢你的作品  -谢谢
-I'm a great admirer of yours. -Thank you.
卡普麦斯特先生
Kapellmeister Bonno. Signore.
我的荣幸
My pleasure.
我们的歌剧院长  罗森保伯爵
The Director of Opera, Count Orsini-Rosenberg.
这绝对是我的荣幸
Sir, yes. The honor is mine, absolutely!
这是我们的宫廷作曲家  萨列里大师
Here is our illustrious court composer...Maestro Salieri.
我在你很小时就见过你了
At last, such immense joy!
我很熟悉您的作品
I know your work well.
我事实上修改过您的一首作品
You know, I composed some variations on a melody of yours.
-真的?  哪一首?  -《Mio Caro Adone》  -我真是受宠若惊
-Really? Which one? -"Mio Caro Adone." I'm flattered.
那是一首奇怪的小品不过有一些不错的效果
A funny tune, but it yielded good things.
他现在回报你的赞美
And now he has returned the compliment.
萨列里为你作了一首欢迎你的进行曲
Herr Salieri composed this little march for you.
真的?
Really?
先生  谢谢你了
Grazie, signore.
就是这样子了
Well, there it is.
现在我们来谈正事莫扎特  我们要举行一场歌剧
Down to business. We're going to commission an opera from you.
你觉得怎么样?
What do you say?
陛下
Majesty!
我们最后有无作成决定  是采德文或意大利文?
Did we vote in the end for German or Italian?
事实上我们最后较倾向  意大利文
Sire, if you remember, we did finally incline to Italian.
有吗?
Did we?
我认为这还没有决定  陛下
I don't think it was really decided, Your Majesty.
-德文...拜托...我们写德文的  -为什么?
-German. Please let it be German. -Why so?
因为我早己找到最精彩的歌词
Because I've already found the most wonderful libretto.
我看过吗?
Have I seen it?
院长陛下应该没有!  我的意思是  这剧本是全新的
I don't think you have, Herr Direktor. It's quite new.
我会立刻拿来给你看
-I'll show it to you immediately of course.
介绍一下
Well...
介绍一下故事吧!
tell us about it. Tell us the story.
相当吸引人有趣的  陛下
Well, it's quite amusing, Majesty.
背景是在  整个故事的背景是在...
It's set The whole thing is set in a....
是的  那里呢?
Yes? Where?
在一个妓院里  陛下
In a harem, Majesty. In a seraglio.
-你的意思是说土耳其?  -没错!  正是
-You mean in Turkey? -Yes, exactly.
那何以特别要用德文呢?
Then why especially does it have to be in German?
其实也不一定要  如果你们喜欢的话也可以用土耳其文
It doesn't, especially. It could be in Turkish if you really want.
莫扎特  言语不是重点了
No, my dear fellow, the language is not finally the point.
你认为这类剧情真的适合在国家剧院上演?
Do you really think that subject is appropriate for a national theater?
为什么不呢?  会很有趣的
Why not? It's charming.
我不会真的让妓女露出...
I mean, I won't actually show concubines exposing their....
这绝对不失礼  它是非常崇高的  陛下
It's not indecent. It's highly moral, Majesty.
它充满德意志精神与价值观
It's full of proper German virtues.
对不起!  陛下  什么是德意志精神?
Excuse me, Majesty, but what do you think these could be?
我是一个外国人  愿闻其详
Being a foreigner, I'd love to learn.
那么  莫扎特告诉他什么是德意志精神
Well, tell him, Mozart. Name us a German virtue.
-爱  陛下  -爱!
-Love, sire. -Oh, love!
当然  我们意大利人不懂爱
Of course, in Italy we know nothing about love.
不  我想你不知道的
No, I don't think you do.
我指看意大利歌剧时  只见男高音在吼叫尖叫
Watching Italian opera, all those male sopranos screeching...
一对痴肥的情侣在那里翻白眼  抛媚眼  那不叫爱  那是垃圾
stupid, fat couples rolling their eyes about. That's not love. It's rubbish!
陛下  你选语言
Majesty, you choose the language.
我的工作是使这成为最优秀的歌剧
I'll set it to the finest music ever offered a monarch.
好吧!  就这么决定了!  就选德语吧
Well, there it is. Let it be German.
-这是给你的-陛下要就留着  我全记在脑子了
-This is yours. -Keep it. It's already here in my head.
什么?  才听一次就记牢了?
What? On one hearing only?
我想是吧  陛下
I think so, sire. Yes.
弹给我们听
Show us.
接下来都一样
The rest is just the same, isn't it?
这里好像不太顺
That doesn't really work, does it?
你有没有试过....
Did you try...?
是不是应该比较...
Shouldn't it be a bit more...?
或这样子比较好?
Or this?
没错!
This. Yes.
你认为如何?
Better? What do you think?
我所要作的  只是以音乐赞美主
All I ever wanted was to sing to God.
他赐我那分渴望
He gave me that longing...
却又把我变成哑巴  为什么?
and then made me mute. Why?
告诉我原因
Tell me that.
若他真不要我以音乐赞美他
If he didn't want me to praise him with music...
为什么要给我那分渴望
why implant the desire...
就像我对生理上的欲望一样
like a lust in my body?
然后又否定我应有的才能
And then deny me the talent?
卡瓦里瑞夫人来上课了  大师
Madame Cavalieri is here for her lesson, sir.
怎么样?
Well...?
你喜欢吗?
How do you like it?
是土耳其样式
It's Turkish.
我发型师说今年流行的是土耳其风格
My hairdresser said everything this year's going to be Turkish.
他真是这么说?
Does he?
告诉我他今天还给你说了什么?
What else did he tell you today?
来吧  告诉我一些传闻
Come, come! Give me some gossip.
我听说你看到莫扎特
Well, I heard you met Herr Mozart.
维也纳的消息传得真快
News travels fast in Vienna.
而且他奉命写一出歌剧  是真的吗?
And he's been commissioned to write an opera. Is it true?
-是的  -有没有留给我的角色?
-Yes. -Is there a part in it for me?
-没有  -你怎么知道
-No. -How do you know?
你知道背景在那吗?  那里?
-Do you know where it's set, my dear? -Where?
妓院
In a harem.
那是什么?  妓女院
-What's that? -A brothel.
来吧
Come.
我们开始吧!
Let's begin.
他长得如何?  莫扎特?
-What does he look like? -Mozart?
-可能会令你大失所望  -怎么说?
-You might be disappointed. -Why?
外表和才华往往不是搭配的
Looks and talent don't always go together, Katerina.
大师  外表我不在乎
Looks don't concern me, maestro.
有品味的女人在乎的只是才华
Only talent interests a woman of taste.
我们继续吧!
Shall we continue?
她就在台上
There she was.
我不知道他们何时认识 怎么认识的 她站在那里!
I don't know where they met or how. There she stood!
那里  舞台上  让众人欣赏
On stage, for all to see.
那只贪婪的黄莺一样炫耀给大家看
Showing off like the greedy songbird she was.
10分钟的延长音阶
Ten minutes of ghastly scales. Arpeggios!
上上下下  好像游乐场的烟火  忽上忽下  随之跳动
Whizzing up and down like fireworks at a fairground.
我知道我爱那女人
Understand, I was in love with the girl.
可是我对你发誓
Or at least in lust.
我碰都没有碰过她
And I swear to you, I never laid a finger on her.
同样的  我也不能忍受他人碰她
All the same, I couldn't bear to think of anyone else touching her.
尤其不能忍受那家伙
Least of all, "the creature."
太好了  夫人  你真是我们舞台上的珠宝
Brava, madame! You are an ornament to our stage.
谢谢陛下
Your Majesty.
莫扎特先生  杰作
Well, Herr Mozart. A good effort.
这真的是太杰出了
Well, decidedly that.
太杰出了!  你今天晚上令我们...
An excellent effort! You have shown us something...
大开眼界  是很新
-...quite new tonight. -It is new.
-很新?  -是的
-It is, isn't it, sire? -Yes, indeed.
是很新  殿下  你真的很喜欢吗?
So then, you liked it? You really liked it, sire?
当然喜欢  太精彩了
Well, of course I did! It's very good!
只不过有一点...
Of course, now and then, just now and then...
它好像摸到某种...
it seemed a touch....
你什么意思  陛下
What do you mean, sire?
我是说  事情我该如何说呢?
Well, I mean, occasionally, it seems to have....
我是说  有时显得似乎...
How shall one say...?
我该怎么说呢?
How shall one say, direktor?
-太多音节了 陛下?  -对!  太多音符
-Too many notes, Majesty? -Exactly. Very well put.
我不太明白
-Too many notes. -I don't understand.
音符是我所要的不多也不少
There are just as many notes as I required, neither more nor less.
亲爱的伙伴  事实上
My dear fellow, there are in fact...
耳朵在夜晚所听的音符很有限
only so many notes the ear can hear in an evening.
我想这么说应该对吧?  宫廷作曲家
I think I'm right in saying that, aren't I, court composer?
是的  是的  陛下!
Yes. On the whole, yes, Majesty.
真是太荒谬了
This is absurd!
亲爱的年轻人  别难过!  你的作品是天才之作
Young man, don't take it too hard. Your work is ingenious.
非常地杰出
It's quality work.
只不过音符太多了  如此而己  只要删除一些就完美了
And there are simply too many notes. Just cut a few and it'll be perfect.
你认为应该删除哪一些呢?
Which few did you have in mind?
我亲爱的沃尔夫冈!
Wolfgang, my dear!
陛下  这是韦伯夫人  她是我的房东
-Wolfgang! -Majesty, this is Frau Weber. She's my landlady.
-女性观众迷  -陛下  真是荣幸
-Enchanted, madame. -Sire, such an honor!
这是我女儿康斯汀
This is my dear daughter, Constanze.
她是莫扎特先生的未婚妻  真的?
-She's the fiancée of Herr Mozart. -Really?
真是迷人!  请上来
How charming. Please.
你们什么时候结婚?
Well...when do you marry? -Well....
我父亲还没有答应
We haven't exactly received my father's consent yet.
我们还未决定
Not entirely. Not altogether.
-对不起  你几岁了  -二十六岁
-Excuse me, but how old are you? -26.
我建议你娶了这迷人的小姐
My advice is for you to marry this charming young lady...
-和我们一起住在维也纳  -你看!  你看!
-...and stay with us in Vienna. -You see?
我也这么告诉他  但他不听
I told him that, but he won't listen to me.
陛下  你真是提出了...
Your Majesty, you give such wonderful...
这么棒的皇家建议  我可不可以...
such royal advice. May I...?
就是这样子了
Well, there it is.
可不可以去拿点水来
Wolfie, will you get some water?
去拿点水来!
Will you get some water, please?
快拿点水来!
Wolfie, get some water!
借过  借过
Excuse me. Excuse me.
你知道吗?
Did you know?
-什么?  -婚事
-What? -The marriage.
和你有什么关系?
What does it matter to you?
没事  他想娶谁就娶谁  和我无关
Nothing. He can marry who he pleases, I don't give a damn.
我看起来怎样?
How was I?
你风华美丽
You were sublime.
你觉得那音乐怎么样?
And what did you think of the music?
非常好
Extremely clever.
卡塔尼娜  我...
Katerina, I
对不起
Excuse me.
那女人还躺在地上吗?
Is that woman still lying on the floor?
-不  她没事  -这样我就放心了
-No, she's fine. -Oh, I'm so relieved.
亲爱的莫扎特  恭喜
Dear Mozart, my sincere congratulations.
你喜欢吗?  要是我不呢?
-Did you like it then? -How could I not?
这是当代维也纳最好的音乐  是吗?
It's the best music in Vienna today, don't you agree?
她在床上一定是眼花缭乱
She must be dazzling in bed.
我敢肯定她是艺术鉴定的行家
I assume she's the virtuoso in that department.
你娶她那样的人也不足为奇
No other reason why you'd marry someone like that.
请进
Come in.
抱歉  妈妈的身体不是很舒服
Excuse me. Wolfie, Mom isn't feeling very well.
我们能回家吗?  好的
-Can we go home? -Yes.
不  你现在不能带他走
No, no, no. You can't take him away now.
今晚是属于他的
This is his night.
莫扎特  你不给我们介绍一下?
Won't you introduce us, Wolfgang?
对不起  晚安
Excuse us, Fr?ulein. Good night, signore.
在那个时候我就知道
At that moment I knew, beyond any doubt...
他掌握了她
he'd had her.
那家伙夺走了我亲爱的女人
The creature had had my darling girl.
真是难以令人了解!
It was incomprehensible!
上帝的旨意为何?
What was God up to?
我有可能去尝试吗?
Was it possible I was being tested?
上帝期望我得到原谅
Was God expecting me to offer forgiveness...
在面对所有事的时候吗?
in the face of every offense?
不管有多痛苦?
No matter how painful?
这是非常有可能的
It's very possible.
但为何是他?
But why him?
为何选择莫扎特来教我谦卑呢?
Why choose Mozart to teach me lessons in humility?
我心中对那年轻人充满恨意
My heart was filling up...with such hatred for that little man.
因此我一生中第一次
For the first time in my life, I began to know...
心中有了残暴的想法
really...violent thoughts.
每天  有时好几个小时  我会祈祷
Every day, sometimes for hours, I would pray.
上帝
Lord...
求求你
please...
送他
send him away...
回沙兹堡
back to Salzburg.
他的原因
For his sake...
也是我的原因
as well as mine.
-不  我不要他回来  -尊敬的阁下
-No! I won't have him back. -But, Your Grace
你儿子是被宠坏又任性的坏孩子
Your son is an unprincipled, spoiled, conceited brat!
我承认  这是事实
Yes, sir...that is the truth.
但是不要责怪他  这全都是我的错
But don't blame him. The fault is mine, entirely.
我是太溺爱他了
I was too indulgent with him.
求求您  陛下
Please, Your Grace?
再给他一次机会?
Give him one more chance?
好吧  你可以再试试看
You have leave to try.
谢谢你  谢谢
God bless, Your Grace! I thank Your Grace.
我有紧急的事要告诉你
I thank you!
我要来维也纳了
I write to you with urgent news. I'm coming to Vienna.
直到你我见面之前...不准结婚
Take no further steps towards marriage until we meet.
若你尊敬一生尽心为你设想的父亲
As you honor the father who has devoted his life to yours...
就照我说的去作  并等我的到来
do as I bid, and await my coming.
现在我见证你们结成神圣的婚姻关系.
I now join you in the holy bonds of matrimony.
上帝与你们同在
Those whom God hath joined together...
使你们永远不分离
let no man put asunder.
敬爱的父亲  记得你说过
Beloved father:
维也纳是音乐家之都  征服这里  就等于征服全欧
You say Vienna is the musicians' city. To conquer here is to conquer Europe.
有妻相伴  我们必能成功 有朝一日我功成名就
With my wife, I can do it. One day, when I'm wealthy...
你可以过来和我们一起住  我们会非常快乐
you'll live with us, and we'll be so happy.
早安  宫廷作曲家  这是我侄女  伊丽莎白公主
Good morning. This is my niece, Princess Elizabeth.
尊贵的殿下
Your Highness.
她请我推荐给她一合适音乐教师
She's asked me to recommend a music instructor.
-我想我己有一个很好的构想  -陛下!
-I've come up with an excellent idea. -Your Majesty!
那真是我的荣幸
It would be such a tremendous honor!
我想到莫扎特  你觉得如何?
I was thinking of Herr Mozart. What is your view?
那倒是个不错的主意  但是陛下...
It's an interesting idea, Majesty, but....
什么?
Yes?
我所关切是要使您免受任何因偏袒而受到的伤害
My concern is to protect you...from any hint of favoritism.
偏袒?
Favoritism.
-怎么了  大臣?  -什么怎么了
-What is this? -What is what?
当个13岁女孩的教师 还得把作品交给某些呆子委员会审查?
Why must I submit samples of my work to a committee to teach a girl?
因为这是陛下的旨意
Because His Majesty wishes it.
陛下在生我的气?
Is the emperor angry with me?
-刚好相反  -那他为何不指派我?
-Quite the contrary. -Then why not appoint me to the post?
莫扎特  维也纳作曲家不只你一人
You are not the only composer in Vienna.
没错  但我却是其中最好的
No. But I'm the best.
莫扎特
Mozart.
谦虚一点对你会更有益
A little modesty might suit you better.
委员会有哪些人?
Who is on this committee?
卡普麦斯特  罗林保伯爵  还有宫廷作曲家
Kapellmeister Bonno, Count Orsini-Rosenberg and Salieri.
一想即知  意大利人  当然  总是意大利人
Naturally, the Italians! Of course, always the Italians!
他们全是不了解音乐的白痴
They're all musical idiots!
-你要他们审核我的作品  -年轻人
-And you want them to judge my music? -Young man...
问题很简单  若你想得到这职位
the issue is quite simple. If you want this position...
必须拿出作品和其它作曲家一起送审
you must submit your stuff, along with all your colleagues.
一定要吗?
-Must I? -Mm-hm.
可惜我作不到
Well, I won't.
这样的日子我们怎么过?
How are we supposed to live?
要我在大街上乞讨吗?
Do you want me to beg on the streets?
别傻了
Don't be stupid.
-他们想看到的只是你的作品  -糟糕
-All they want to see is your work. -Shit.
你是怎么啦?  闭嘴!  给我闭嘴
-What's wrong with that? -Shut up! Just shut up.
一个王室学生  整个维也纳都会感到震惊的
One royal pupil, and all of Vienna will come flocking.
他们什么都会
They'll come anyway.
不  他们不会的  他们喜欢我在这
-No, they won't. -They love me here.
-我对这个城市很清楚  -你是万事通,对吧!
-I know how things work in this city. -You know everything, don't you?
-什么事?  -抱歉  先生
-Yes? -Excuse me, sir.
-有位小姐坚持要见您  -是谁?
-A lady insists on talking to you. -Who?
她没说  只是说有急事
She didn't say, but she says it's urgent.
失陪  亲爱的
Excuse me, my dear.
我能帮你什么忙?
How can I help you?
-莫扎特夫人?  -我是为了我丈夫来的
-Frau Mozart? -I've come on behalf of my husband.
我带他部分作品  让他更有机会得到皇室的工作
I brought samples of his work so he can be considered for the appointment.
真是太好了  可是他为何不自己来?
How charming, but why did he not come himself?
先生  他非常的忙
Well, he's terribly busy, sir.
我知道
I understand.
当然我一有空就会看
I will look at them the moment I can.
这是我的荣幸  请向他致以我最温暖的问候
It will be an honor. Please give him my warmest regards.
如果你现在就看会不会太麻烦?
Would it be too much trouble to ask you to look at them now?
-我在这里等  -现在恐怕...没空
-While I wait. -I'm afraid I'm not at leisure...this precise moment.
就先放我这儿  我保证很安全
Leave them with me. I assure you, they will be safe.
我恐怕不能这么作
I really cannot do that, sir.
事实是  他不知我来这里
You see, he doesn't know I'm here.
他没叫你来?
Then he didn't send you?
是我自作主张
No, sir. This was my own idea.
-我知道了  -先生  我们穷途末路了
-I see. -Sir, we're desperate.
我们真的需要这份工作
We really need this job.
我先生入不敷出
My husband spends far more than he can ever earn.
我不是说他懒情  他一点也不懒  他整天都在工作
I don't mean that he's lazy, because he works all day long.
只是...他不实际
It's just that he's not practical.
他就是守不住钱  这真是太可笑了
Money simply slips through his fingers. It's ridiculous.
要不要吃些东西
Let me offer you some refreshment.
你知道这是什么吗?
Do you know what these are?
维纳斯的乳头
Capezzoli di Venere! Nipples of Venus.
这是包白兰地糖的核桃  吃一个吧
They're Roman chestnuts in brandied sugar. Try one. Go on!
你一定会吓一跳
They're quite surprising.
很完美
They're wonderful!
多谢你了  先生
Thank you very much, Your Excellency.
别那么称呼我
Don't keep calling me that.
这样子有距离感
Keeps me at such a distance.
我不是生下来就当宫廷作曲家
I wasn't born a court composer, you know.
我来自一个小镇
I'm from a small town.
正和你先生一样
Just like your husband.
你确定你不能留下这些资料
Are you sure you can't...
改天再来?
leave this and come back again?
听来很不错
It's very tempting, sir.
不过恐怕不行
But it's impossible, I'm afraid.
若他发现这些不见了  一定会发疯的
He'd be frantic if he knew they were missing.
这些都是原稿
You see, they're all originals.
-原稿?  -是的  他从来不会复写
-Originals? -Yes, sir. He doesn't make copies.
这些全是原稿?
These...are originals?
太不可思议了!
Astounding!
简直不敢相信!
It was actually. It was beyond belief.
这些乐稿全是唯一的版本
These were first and only...
全然没有任何修改的痕迹
drafts of music.
一点也没有
But they showed no corrections of any kind. Not one.
他只是将在脑中已完成的曲调
He had simply written down music...
一成不变的写下来而巳
already finished in his head.
一页接着一页如同是在听写一般
Page after page of it. As if he were just taking dictation.
这是前所未见的悦耳音乐
And music...finished as no music is ever finished.
更动任何一个音符就不完美
Displace one note...and there would be diminishment.
更动一小节  结构性就会瓦解
Displace one phrase, and the structure would fall.
我现在了解...
It was clear to me...
那夜在大主教家中听到的音乐
that sound I had heard in the archbishop's palace...
绝不是偶然的
had been no accident.
这些乐稿再次呈现了上帝的声音
Here again was the very voice of God.
我一小节一小节的看
I was staring through the cage...
看那些笔下的音符
of those meticulous ink strokes...
我看到的是完美无暇的音乐
at an absolute beauty.
写得不好吗?
Is it not good?
这简直是奇迹
It is miraculous.
是的  他很以自己的作品为傲
Yes, he's very proud of his work.
那么你会帮助我们吗?
So you will help us?
我明晚和国王商量一下
I dine with the emperor tomorrow evening.
我的一句话  就能给他谋个位子了
One word from me and the post is his.
谢谢  真是太谢谢你了!
Thank you, Your Excellency! Thank you!
今晚回来
Come back tonight.
-今晚?  -一个人来
-Tonight? -Alone.
干什么?
What for?
回报性的服务
Some service deserves service in return.
不干吗?
No?
-你什么意思?  -不是很明显吗?
-What do you mean? -Isn't it obvious?
一个所有维也纳人都想得到的职位
It's a post all Vienna seeks.
如果你想你丈夫得到的话  今晚过来
If you wish it for your husband, come tonight.
先生  我是个已婚女人
I'm a married woman, sir.
那就算了
Then don't.
你自己看着办
It's up to you.
别含含糊糊的  这就是代价
And not to be vague, that is the price.
没有怜借之神  神父
There is no God of mercy, Father.
只有折磨
Just a God of torture.
夜晚到来了
Evening came.
我坐在那儿  不知她是否会回来
I sat there, not knowing whether she would return or not.
我从未这么祈祷过
I prayed as I had never prayed before.
上帝啊
Dear God...
救救我吧
enter me now.
给我一首真实的音乐
Fill me with one piece of true music.
─首用你的呼吸写的曲子  好让我知道你是爱我的
One piece with your breath in it, so I know that you love me.
暗示一下你的帮助  我会把我的暗示给莫扎特的
Show me one sign of your favor, and I will show mine to Mozart.
我会帮他在皇宫里弄个位子的
I will get him the royal position.
救救我
Enter me.
求求你
Please.
Please!
什么事?
Yes?
先生  那位小姐回来了
That lady is back, sir.
带她进来
Show her in.
我来了
I'm here.
我丈夫参加音乐会去了
My husband has gone to a concert.
他根本没有想到我会很开心
He didn't think I would enjoy it.
我们去哪里?
Well, where shall we go?
待在这里吗?
Should we stay here?
你还想看吗?
Do you still want to look at these?
还是我们别再烦了?
Or don't we need to bother anymore?
我想还是不用了
Suppose we don't, really.
带这个女人出去
Show this woman out.
史坦丝
Stanzi.
怎么啦?
What is it?
怎么回事?  告诉我
What's the matter? Tell me.
告诉我
Tell me.
我爱你
I love you.
从今起  我们誓不两立
From now on, we are enemies.
你上帝和我
You and I.
因为你选了一个好色下流的小孩
Because you choose for your instrument...
作为传播你声音的工具
a boastful, lustful, smutty, infantile boy...
而给我的只是让我能够了解他的才华
and give me for reward only the ability to recognize the incarnation.
因为你不公正
Because you are unjust...
不公平
unfair...
不仁慈
unkind...
我发誓要拒绝你
I will block you. I swear it.
我要全力伤害你世上的代言人
I will hinder and harm your creature on earth...
我要尽我的能力去害他我要毁了你的工具
as far as I am able.
我不喜欢和平民音乐家一起谈话
I don't like to talk against a fellow musician.
当然了
Of course not.
我必须告诉你
I have to tell you.
莫扎特和年轻小姐在一起  对他我不是很放心
Mozart is not entirely to be trusted alone with young ladies.
真的吗?
Really?
我的一个学生  一个非常年轻的歌手
One of my own pupils, a very young singer...
玛莉亚
Maria Theresa Paradis...
对我说她被...
told me she was....
是什么?
Well, what?
性骚扰
Molested, Majesty.
一节课中两次
Twice, in the course of the same lesson.
莫扎特先生在宫厅等你
There is a Herr Mozart waiting for you in the salon.
-他们选了谁?  -兹姆
-Whom did they choose? -Herr Zummer.
兹姆?
Herr Zummer?
但他是个大傻瓜
But the man's a fool! He's a total mediocrity.
不  不  他已经超过了平庸之才
No, no. He has yet to achieve mediocrity.
我不能失去这个职位  就这么简单
I can't lose this post. I simply can't.
请你帮个忙
Excellency, please.
我们到宫廷去  你可以和国王说说
Let's go to the palace. You can talk to the emperor...
告诉他选择兹姆是错误的
and tell him that Herr Zummer is an awful choice.
由他来教公主简直就是在害她
He could do musical harm to the princess.
这个世上  除了你和我  没有谁会害她的
Between us, no one in the world could do musical harm to the princess.
我必须有学生
Look...I must have pupils.
没有学生  简直想像不出
Without pupils, I can't manage.
你不是说你很穷吧?
You don't mean you're living in poverty?
不  但我已经倾家荡产
No, but I'm broke.
这怎么可能?
Well, how is this possible?
我听说你的音乐会很成功
I hear your concerts are quite successful.
他们惊人的成功
They're stupendously successful.
你没有座位  问题是没有人雇你
You can't get a seat. But no one will hire me.
他们想听我演奏  但却不让我教他们的女儿  好像我是个魔鬼
They want to hear me play, but they won't let me teach their daughters, as if I was a fiend.
讲真的...
Seriously...
我能跟你借钱吗?
is there any chance you could manage a loan?
只有六个月  最多八个月
Only for six months. Eight, at the most.
你想六到八个月中改变你的命运?
You expect your fortunes to change in six or eight months?
不管事实怎样  我会试试
As a matter of fact, I do.
我做的事会像炸弹一样在欧洲爆炸
I am working on something that will explode like a bomb all over Europe.
我会是维也那最富有的人我会双倍付给你
I'll be the richest man in Vienna. I'll pay you back double. Anything.
你说条件
You name the terms.
好  多么刺激呀
Well, how exciting.
告诉我多一些
Tell me more.
-好  我感兴趣
-It's a bit of a secret. -Come, come. I'm interested.
-这很好吃  这是什么?
This is delicious. What is it?
冰奶酪加糖
It's cream cheese mixed with sugar...
加了浪姆酒  奶酪片
suffused with rum. Crema Mascarpone Speciale.
意大利的
Italian.
原谅我  我们有一种爱国的感觉
Forgive me. We all have patriotic feelings of some kind.
我需要两百弗罗林
Two thou
两百  是我全部所需要的
Two hundred florins. That's all I need.
一百?
A hundred.
五十?
Fifty.
你到底打算做些什么事?
What exactly are you working on?
真的不好说
Really, I can't say.
我想你不应该在维也纳成为一个负债人  莫扎特
I don't think you should become known in Vienna as a debtor, Mozart.
总之
However...
我可以给你推荐一个人
I know a distinguished gentleman I can recommend, and...
他有个女儿
he has a daughter.
别吵!
Quiet! Quiet!
莫扎特先生
Herr Mozart.
欢迎!  别介意  没事的
Welcome. Pay no attention, they're impossible.
我像对待自己的孩子般对待它们
I treat them just like my own children.
它们当中你要我教谁?
Which of them do you wish me to teach?
真幽默
That's funny.
你真有趣
You're a funny fellow.
这是乐器  希望你会喜欢
This is the instrument. I hope it's to your satisfaction.
他当然会喜欢了
MICHAEL: Of course it'll be to his satisfaction.
来  我们来听听音乐
Come, we're going to listen to some music. Come!
乖孩子
Good boy.
现在
Now.
请你弹一首我听听  好让我心里有底
Please play me something, just to give me an idea.
随便什么都行
Anything will do.
弹啊
Just go ahead.
就当我们不在
Just as if we weren't here.
一点就行了  弹给听众听对吗  莫扎特先生?
Part of music, getting used to an audience. Right, Herr Mozart?
或许我们离开会好些
Perhaps it would be better if we were left alone.
我们都觉得有点害差
We're both a little shy.
弹
Play.
我叫你弹!  迈克尔  拜托
-I said play! -Michael, please.
或许我先弹  可以鼓舞小姐
Perhaps if I play first, it might encourage the Fr?ulein.
让我试试  好吗?
Why don't you let me try?
别叫!  别叫!  它一听到音乐就大叫
Stop it! Stop! He always howls when he hears music.
要打破他们这个习惯!
We've got to break him of that habit.
We've got to break them of their habit!
弹奏!
Play. Please.
莫扎特先生  请你弹奏  我求你了
Herr Mozart, play. Please, I beg you.
对了  对了
That's it. That's it.
继续!
Keep playing!
继续!  对了!
Keep playing! That's it!
莫扎特  太精彩了!
Mozart, that's wonderful! Wonderful!
下次要我教你其他的狗  请通知我一声
Next time you wish me to instruct another of your dogs, let me know.
再见  小姐  太太  先生  再见
Goodbye, Fr?ulein. Goodbye, madam. Goodbye, sir.
爸爸?
Papa?
爸爸!
Papa!
你怎么来了?
Why are you here?
不欢迎我来吗?
Am I not welcome?
当然欢迎了  爸爸  欢迎你!
Of course, welcome. Papa, welcome! Welcome!
你好瘦  你太太难道不喂你吗?
You're very thin. Doesn't your wife feed you?
她当然会喂好一整天好像填鸭子一样
Of course she feeds me. She stuffs me like a goose all day!
她不在家吗
Is she not here?  No, she had to help her mother.
不  她去照顾她妈了她就是这样的人
She's like that.
我岳母是很好的人
Her mother's a very sweet woman, you'll
我不知你在家
I didn't know you were home.
甜心  这是我父亲
Stanzi, this is my father.
我们会等一下...
We'll wait. We'll wait.
你现在起床好吗  亲爱的?
Why don't you get up now, my darling?
她实在是累坏了可怜的女人  你也知道我散漫成性我很邋遢
She's very tired, poor creature. You know me. I'm such a pig.
帮我打扫可不是一件容易的事
It's not easy cleaning up after me.
你们难道没有女佣吗
Don't you have a maid?
没有  如我们要  我们可请一个
Oh. No. We could if we wanted...
不过史坦丝不想她坚持一切都要自己做
but Stanzi insists on doing everything herself.
你的经济状况如何?
How is your...financial situation?
再好不过了
Couldn't be better.
这和我昨天听的不一样
That's not what I hear.
你是什么意思?  我们很好啊!
What do you mean? It's wonderful.
真的  大家都很喜欢我
Really, it's marvelous! People love me here.
他们说你欠了很多钱
They say you have debts.
谁
Who?
谁说的!
Who says that?
真恶毒的谎话
That's a malicious lie!
你有学生吗?
Do you have pupils?
我不要学生
I don't want pupils!
他们会防碍我
They get in the way.
我需要空出时间专心作曲
I have to have time for composition.
作曲是赚不到钱的你也知道
Composition doesn't pay. You know that.
这首可以赚得到!
That one will.
那是什么?
What's that?
是秘密
It's a secret.
什么秘密?  你不需要对我保密
Secret? You don't have secrets from me.
不!  不!  不!
No.
拜托  我不要你看  我还不要任何人看
No! Please! I don't want you to see it. I don't want anyone to see it.
不过你一定会替我骄做的  爸爸
You'll be so proud of me.
这会是我最棒的作品这是有史以来最...
It'll be the best thing I've ever done. The best thing anyone
啊!  她出来了!
There she is!
看看她!  多美啊!
Look at her! Isn't she beautiful? Now, Papa, confess it.
爸爸  说实话她是不是最美的媳妇?  别闹了...
-Could you want a prettier daughter? -Stop it, Wolfie!
我看起来很糟
I look dreadful.
你...
Are you...
怀孕了吗?
expecting?
是的  是不是棒极了?  我们非常高兴
-Yes, I am. -Isn't it marvelous? We're delighted.
-莫扎特先生可不可以帮你倒杯茶?  -茶  谁喝茶!
-May I offer you some tea? -Who wants tea? Let's go out!
我们出去大吃一顿  你不会想喝茶吧  爸爸
This calls for a feast. You don't want tea, do you, Papa?
我知道  我们去跳舞爸爸喜欢跳舞
I know! Let's go dancing. Papa loves parties, don't you?
真是无聊!  喝茶
How can you be so boring? Tea!
快点  爸爸  快点
Come on, Papa. Hurry!
我们走  美好的一天
Here we go. Good day.
现在
Now!
我的名字是惩罚!  我的名字是惩罚!
I name the penalty! I name the penalty!
输的要罚!
And the penalty is....
-我们的处罚是...-把腿给大家看!
-Give her a good one! -Show us your legs!
快点  快点
Come on, come on!
只是个游戏罢了  爸爸
It's just a game, Papa.
谢谢
Thank you.
现在!
Now!
莫扎特先生你决定怎么罚你儿子吧
Herr Mozart, why don't you name your son's penalty?!
爸爸  说吧!
Yes, Papa. Name it.
我一定会作的  一定会
Name it. I'll do anything you say. Anything.
我要你跟我回沙德堡
I want you to come back to Salzburg with me.
爸爸  规则是处罚必需在现场能够执行
The penalty must be performed in the room.
我觉得这个游戏很无聊  我不要再玩了
I'm tired of this game.
但处罚是什么?  必需要处罚我...
But my penalty! I've got to have a penalty!
我来决定处罚...
I name a penalty!
你的处罚是...
The penalty is...
用巴哈的风格来...
you shall play our tune...
演奏我们的小调
in the manner of Johann Sebastian Bach!
把他翻过来
-Turn him over! -Over?!
现在倒着弹
Now you play it backwards!
再来一首吧!  和格拉克一样的演奏
-Another one! Another one! -Play it like Gluck!
-无聊!  -韩德尔的!
-Boring. Another! -Handel!
那我也不喜欢  再一个
I don't like him! Another one!
萨列里的作品!
Play Salieri.
这可是个挑战
Now, that is a challenge! That is a challenge.
请让让...
Please! Please!
继续吧!  取笑我吧!  笑吧
Go on. Mock me. Laugh!
笑我的不是莫扎特
That was not Mozart laughing, Father.
是上帝!  神父
That was God.
经由那荒唐的笑声在取笑我
That was God laughing at me through that obscene giggle.
继续笑我  笑啊!
Go on, signore. Laugh.
笑我的平庸展现给大家看
Show my mediocrity for all to see.
有一天  我也会笑你的
One day I will laugh at you.
在我离开世间前
Before I leave this earth...
我会笑你的
I will laugh at you.
-沃夫  -什么事?
-Wolfie? -What?
有个年轻女孩来看你
There's a young girl here to see you.
干什么?
What does she want?
她不说  她说要直接跟你说
She won't talk to me. She says she has to speak to you.
糟糕
Damn.
什么事?
Yes?
-你是莫扎特吗?  -是的
-Are you Herr Mozart? -That's right.
我叫萝拉  我是个女佣
My name is Lorl, sir. I'm a maidservant.
有个你的祟拜者付我钱来服侍你
I was asked to come here and offer my services to you.
他不希望您知道他的名字
They'll be paid for by an admirer of yours who wishes to remain...anonymous.
这是你的主意吗?  爸爸
Is this your idea, Papa?
我?
Mine?
-你是不是在和开我玩笑?  -我这一辈子没见过这女孩
-Are you playing a trick on me? -I've never seen this girl.
-你是某种玩笑吗?  -绝对不是  先生
-Is this some kind of joke? -Not at all, sir.
小姐  这是不可能的
Young woman, this won't do.
无论对方多么慷慨我的儿子不能接受这种做法
My son can't accept such an offer, no matter how generous...
-除非他知道幕后的人是谁  -可是我真的不能告诉你
-...unless he knows who's behind it. -I can't tell you that, sir.
-太荒唐了-才不呢!
This is ridiculous! -What is ridiculous?
莫扎特在维也纳有许多祟拜者
Wolfie has many admirers in Vienna.
时常有人送礼物来
People send us gifts all the time.
可是不知对方底细怎能接受呢
You cannot accept her without references.
这不关你的事
Well, this is none of your business.
-派你来的人会付薪水吧?  是不是  -没错
-Whoever sent you is going to pay? -That's right.
好极了  现在我们要让一个陌生人进来我们家
Splendid! Now we're going to let a stranger into our house.
我们  谁是我们...
Who is we? Who is letting who?
-你能在外面等一下吗?  -好的!  夫人
-Could you please wait outside? -Yes, ma'am.
听着  老头子!
Look, old man!
我们在你身上花了很多钱  你却只会成天批评我们
We spend a fortune on you, and all you can do is criticize.
-现在你认为...-史坦丝
-And now -Stanzi!
不  他应该要听到  我真是受够了
No! It's right that he should hear! I'm sick to death of it.
我们怎么服侍你都不对
We can't do anything right for you, can we?
你永远再也不必替我作任何事了
You won't have to do anything for me ever again.
我要走了
I'm leaving.
不要  爸爸  放心  我不会留在这儿烦你们
-No, Papa.  I won't stay and be a burden.
没有人认为你是负担
No one calls you that.
是吗?  她就是这么想  她成天就是在睡觉!
She does. She says I sleep all day.
你还不是一样!
And so you do!
只有在吃饭时你才会离开房间
The only time you come out is to eat.
那你要我怎样
Well, what do you expect?
你希望我在这么乱的房间生活吗
Do you expect anyone to walk out into a mess like this every day?
-现在要说我不会管家了  -事实就是!  这屋子总是像猪窝!
-Now I'm a bad housekeeper! -So you are. It's a pigsty.
什么时候开始?
When can you start?
现在  太太
-Right away, ma'am.  Good.
每天晚上都出去  先生
They're out every night, sir.
谢谢
Thank you, sir.
有没有学生来上课
Do any pupils come to the house?
我没看见
Not that I've seen.
那他怎么会有钱花?
Then how does he pay for all this?
他有没有在工作?
Does he work at all?
有  整天都在工作!  他要等到晚上才会出门
Yes, sir. All day long. He never leaves the house till evening.
他就坐在那儿不断的写
He just sits there, writing and writing.
是吗?
Really?
他写些什么?
What is it he's writing?
这个我不知道  先生
I wouldn't know that, sir.
当然你不明白!
Of course not.
你是个乖女孩
You're a good girl.
你为我这么做太好了
You're very kind to do this.
下次他不在家时  让我知道一下
The next time you're sure they'll be out of the house, let me know.
谢谢
Thank you, sir.
我想我知道他如何生活了
I think I found out about the money, sir.
怎么说?
Yes? What?
他这里有七个鼻烟盒我发誓这全都是纯金的
He kept seven snuffboxes in here. I could swear they were all gold.
你看
And now look.
现在只剩一个了
There's only one left.
他在哪里工作?
Where does he work?
在里边  先生
In there, sir.
先生们  我刚刚听说了些消息...
Gentlemen, I've just heard some news...
-可能各位会感兴趣  -什么新闻?
-that may interest you. -What?
莫扎特在写新歌剧  意大利语的
Mozart is writing a new opera. An Italian opera.
意大利语?
Italian?
还不止这样  他选费加洛做为主角
That's not all. He has chosen for his subject, Figaro.
《费加洛婚礼》!
The Marriage of Figaro.
他将那种剧本写曲子?
He's setting that play to music?
是啊!
Yes.
这《费加洛婚礼》是什么剧本
What is this Marriage of Figaro?
那是一出法国的戏剧
It's a French play, Kapellmeister.
是陛下禁止上演的
It has been banned by the emperor.
你确定吗?
You're absolutely sure?
莫扎特先生
Herr Mozart.
大家坐下
Gentlemen, sit down.
莫扎特
Mozart.
你可知我已经宣布法国戏剧《费加洛婚礼》不得体
Are you aware that I have declared the French play Figaro...unsuitable for our theater?
是  我知道
Yes, sire.
我们听说你在写这出歌剧是不是事实?
Yet we hear you're making an opera from it. Is this true?
谁告诉你的?  陛下
Who told you this, Majesty?
你现在没有资格问问题  是不是事实?
It is not your place to ask questions. Is it true?
-是真的吗?
Yes, I....
-是的  我承认
I admit it is.
你可不可以告诉我为什么?
Would you tell me why?
陛下  那只是个喜剧
Majesty, it is only a comedy.
你怎么想并不重要  莫扎特
What you think is scarcely the point.
陛下的想法才重要
It's what His Majesty thinks that counts.
可是  陛下
But, Your Majesty
莫扎特
Mozart...
我是宽大的人
I am a tolerant man.
我不会随便下禁令的  我决定的事都有理由
I do not censor things lightly. When I do, I have good reason.
《费加洛婚礼》是不好的戏剧
Figaro is a bad play.
因为它挑动阶级之间的仇视
It stirs up hatred between classes.
法国就是一例
In France, it has caused only bitterness.
我的亲妹妹安东妮写信给我  说她现在很害怕自己的子民
My sister Antoinette is beginning to be frightened of her own people.
陛下  我对你发誓歌剧已经没有那些成分
I swear, there's nothing like that in the piece.
我把这些都删掉了  我讨厌政治
I've taken out everything that could give offense. I hate politics.
我想你太天真了
I'm afraid you're rather innocent.
在这个动荡时期  我不能冒险让它...
In these dangerous times I cannot afford to provoke our people...
刺激贵族或平民的情绪
simply over a theater piece.
陛下  那只是个谈情说爱的喜剧
Majesty, this is just a frolic. A piece about love.
又是爱情
"Love." Again!
而且是最新潮的
And it's new!
很新  人们会为它而疯迷的
It's entirely new. The people will go mad for it.
我举例说明
I have scenes....
例如第二幕的最后
The end of Act II, for example.
一开始是夫妻吵嘴的对唱
It starts as a duet. A husband and wife quarreling.
突然有阴谋的女佣跑进来  非常有趣的情景
Suddenly, the scheming maid comes in. It's a very funny situation.
二重唱转成三重唱
Duet turns into trio.
然后先生的侍者走进来他与女佣有阴谋
Then the husband's valet comes in.
三重唱变成四重唱
Trio turns into quartet.
然后愚蠢的园丁跑进来四重唱成为五重唱
Then a gardener. Quartet becomes quintet.
然后继续变成...
And so on, on and on.
六重唱  七重唱  八重唱
Sextet, septet, octet.
陛下你猜我能这样维持多久?
How long do you think I can sustain that?
我不知道
I have no idea.
猜看看
Guess.
猜看看  陛下
Guess, Your Majesty.
猜猜看这种过程可以维持多久然后再将它加一倍
Imagine the longest time it could be sustained, then double it.
恩...六分钟?
Well....Six...
七分钟?
seven minutes?
-八分钟?  -二十分钟  陛下
-Eight minutes? -Twenty, sire. Twenty minutes!
二十分钟不断的音乐  完全没有对白
Twenty minutes of continuous music. No recitatives!
只有在歌剧里可以这样处理
Sire, only opera can do this.
戏剧中如果二人以上同时说话
In a play, if more than one person speaks at once...
就只剩下噪音  没有人听得懂
it's just noise.
但在歌剧中  伴随着音乐
But with opera, with music...
二十人同时说话
you can have 20 individuals all talking at the same time.
但不是噪音  而是完美的旋律
It's not noise. It's a perfect harmony!
莫扎特  我们不是在谈音乐
Mozart, music is not the issue here.
没有人怀疑你的才能  我们是在讨论你所选的素材
No one doubts your talent. It's your literary judgment that's in question.
就算没有政治的成份  它仍是一个低俗的剧本
Even without the politics, it would remain a vulgar farce.
不要将你的才能浪费在废料上
Why waste your spirit on such rubbish?
你可以选些更高级的剧本
Surely you can choose more elevated themes.
高级的!  高级!  那是什么意思
Elevated! What does that mean, elevated?
我给这些高级的东西烦死了
I am fed to the teeth with these...
全都是古老  没有生命力的传说
elevated things. Old dead legends.
为何我们一定要不断的只去写有关神的传说?
Why must we go on forever writing of gods and legends?
因为神是不朽的
Because they do. They go on forever.
至少他们代表我们心中的永恒
At least what they represent: the eternal in us.
歌剧是为了使我们更高尚的  莫扎特
Opera is here to ennoble us, Mozart.
就如同你我及陛下是高尚的一样
You and me, just the same as His Majesty.
说得好!  公爵
Bello. Veramente.
为何要高尚  大家诚实一点
"Bello, bello, bello." Come on now, be honest!
你们谁不是比较爱听理发师的话  而不喜欢大力士神话?
You'd rather listen to your hairdresser than Hercules, Horatius or Orpheus.
或是那些大家祟拜的诸神  这些崇高的人连大便都是大理石
People so lofty, they sound as if they shit marble!
什么!
What!
注意你的用词!  莫扎特你太放肆了!
Govern your tongue, Mozart! How dare you!
原谅我  陛下
Forgive me, Majesty.
我是个低俗的人
I'm a vulgar man...
但我保证我的音乐绝不低俗
but I assure you, my music is not.
你是很有热情的人  莫扎特
You are passionate, Mozart...
但你并不能说服我们
but you do not persuade.
陛下  整个歌剧已经完成了
Sire, the whole opera is finished.
你知道我花了多少心血
Do you know how much work went into it?
陛下已经没有耐心了!
His Majesty has been more than patient, signore.
不让我演给你看  如何能说服你
How can I persuade if I can't show it?
够了  莫扎特先生
That will do, Herr Mozart.
就让我告诉你序幕是怎样好了
Just let me tell you how it begins.
我可不可以这么做  陛下?  只是提一下开头
May I just do that, Majesty? Show you how it begins? Just that?
好!
Please.
请看
Look....
有个佣人跪在地上您知道为什么吗?
There's a servant on his knees. Do you know why?
不是因为任何人要他那样  是因为他在测量
Not from oppression. He's measuring a space.
你知道测量什么吗?
Do you know what for?
他结婚用的床
His bed. His wedding bed.
看看是否放得下
To see if it will fit!
莫扎特已经开始彩排了
Well, Mozart is already rehearsing.
既然如此  各位那我们该
In that case, gentlemen, I think....
尽一切可能的帮助他
I think we should help Mozart all we can.
让他不要激怒陛下
And protect him against the emperor's anger.
什么处份?
What anger?
因为芭雷舞啊!
About the ballet.
什么芭雷舞?
What ballet?
陛下不是禁止芭雷舞出现在歌剧
Excuse me...but didn't His Majesty specifically forbid the ballet in his opera?
莫扎特!
Mozart!
什么事?
-Herr Mozart! -Yes?
可不可以借一步说话!  当然可以  院长先生!
-A word with you.  Certainly, Herr Direktor.
现在!  现在!
Now, Herr Mozart!
休息五分钟!
Five minutes, please.
Five minutes!
什么事?
Yes?
你不知道陛下禁止在歌剧中表演芭雷舞吗?
Do you not know that His Majesty has expressly forbidden ballet in operas?
-这不是芭雷舞  这是婚礼舞蹈!  -没错  舞蹈
-It's not a ballet, it's a dance. -Exactly. A dance.
陛下当然不是禁止故事中有跳舞
Surely, His Majesty didn't mean no dancing when it's in the story.
任意解释陛下的意旨是很危险的  把乐谱给我
It's dangerous to interpret his edicts. Give me your score, please.
谢谢!
Thank you.
院长先生  你干什么?  你在干什么?
What are you doing, Herr Direktor?
除去不适合的部分
Taking out what you should never have put in.
求求你
Please. Please!
我没有别人可求了
I have no one else to turn to.
-莫扎特  什么事?  -你不会相信的!
-What is it? -It's unbelievable.
院长将我歌剧的大部份都去除
The direktor has torn up a huge section of my music.
他们说我应该重写
They say I have to rewrite the opera.
但这作品已经很完美了
But it's perfect as it is.
我不能...
I can't...
改写已经是完美的作品
rewrite what's perfect.
求您
Please.
你不能去找他说些好话好吗?
Can't you talk to him?
求您
Please.
我都很讨厌他了  何况是你
Why bother? He's no friend of yours.
我真的想杀了他
I could kill him! I mean, really! Kill him!
我气的将乐谱丢到火炉中
I threw the entire score into the fire, he made me so angry.
-你把乐谱给烧了?  -没有  我太太及时救回来了
-You burned the score? -No, my wife took it out in time.
谢天谢地
Thank God.
这种人可以审核我们的作品真是不公平
It's unfair that a man like that should have power over our work!
但有人却可以控制他
But there are those who have power over him.
我直接跟陛下谈
I think I'll take this up with the emperor.
太好了
Excellency...
真的吗?
would you?
我全心全意的去做  莫扎特
With all my heart, Mozart.
谢谢你
Thank you.
好了!  好了!  我又不是教宗
Please, Herr Mozart. "Please, it's not a holy relic."
当然我什么也没告诉陛下
I don't need to tell you I said nothing, whatever, to the emperor.
我照常去剧场骗骗莫扎特
I went to the theater to tell Mozart something, anything...
突然在第三幕当中
when suddenly, in the middle of the third act...
从不参观排演的陛下竟然来了
to my astonishment, the emperor...who never attended rehearsals, suddenly appeared.
这在干什么?
What is this?
我不了解
I don't understand.
这就是最前卫的吗?
Is it modern?
陛下...
Majesty...
院长将...
the Herr Direktor...
芭雷舞部分的乐曲...除去了
he has removed un balletto...that would have occurred at this place.
为什么?
Why?
这是你的规定
It is your regulation, sire.
歌剧院里不准上演芭蕾舞
No ballet in your opera.
萨列里
Salieri.
你喜欢这样子吗?
Do you like this?
这不是喜不喜欢的问题
It's not a question of liking, Majesty.
你的法律这样规定的
Your own law decrees it, I'm afraid.
看看他们
Well, look at them!
不...这简直是乱来
No! This is nonsense!
-配上音乐再让我看看  -可是  陛下
-Let me see the scene with the music. -But, sire!
这是命令!
Oblige me!
是的  陛下
Yes, Majesty.
可不可以配上音乐再给我们看一次
Can we see the scene with the music, please?
当然可以!  院长先生
Certainly! Certainly, Herr Direktor!
将宫庭那一景弄回来
Bring the palace set back in, please.
还原后的第三幕大胆绝妙
The restored third act...was bold, brilliant.
第四幕...
The fourth...
真是美得不可思议
was astounding.
一位女士...
I saw a woman...
伪装成一位女佣  他先生向她倾诉...
disguised in her maid's clothes hear her husband speak the first...
多年未说的情话
tender words he has offered her in years.
只因为他以为她是别人
Simply because he thinks she is someone else.
我听到充满宽恕的音符散在剧场
I heard the music of true forgiveness filling the theater...
全场听众全部沉醉在那音乐中
conferring on all who sat there, perfect absolution.
上帝又因莫扎特...
God was singing through this little man...
而呈现给世上
to all the world.
从不停止的
Unstoppable.
每一小节都会我觉得失败得更深
Making my defeat more bitter with every passing bar.
然后  你知道发生了什么事
And then, do you know what happened?
奇迹
A miracle!
因为那哈欠
With that yawn...
我的失败转为成功
I saw my defeat turn into a victory.
他还算运气只让陛下打一次哈欠
Mozart was lucky the emperor yawned only once.
如果有三次
Three yawns...
当晚就会停演
and the opera would fail the same night.
两次次的话  最多演一星期
Two yawns, within a week at most.
一次的话  作曲家仍然可以
With one yawn, the composer could still get....
九场!  就只有九场现在就被取消了?
Nine performances! Nine! That's all it's had! Withdrawn!
我知道!
I know, I know.
真是太令人气愤了
It's outrageous.
不过大家要是不喜欢的作品
Still, if the public doesn't like one's work...
我们还是要接受这事实
one has to accept the fact gracefully.
但他们为什么不喜欢!
But what is it that they don't like?
我知道陛下为什么不喜欢
I can speak for the emperor.
因为太长了
You make too many demands on the royal ear.
他只能集中精神的听上一小时  你却要演上个四小时
The poor man can't concentrate for more than an hour. You gave him four.
你认为怎样?
What did you think of it yourself?
你喜欢吗?
Did you like it at all?
很美妙!
I thought it was marvelous.
当然了  这是前无古人之作
Of course. It's the best opera yet written.
我知道
I know it!
他们为什么不来?
Why didn't they come?
你高估了维也纳人的水准
I think you overestimate our dear Viennese, friend.
你甚至没有在歌曲结尾时
You didn't give them a bang at the end of songs...
给他们一些鼓掌的暗示
to let them know when to clap.
我明白了
I know, I know.
也许你该在这方面教我一些
Maybe you should give me some lessons in that.
我不会那么冒昧
I wouldn't presume.
虽然我知道有点冒犯...
Nevertheless, at the risk of imposing...
我想请你看我的新作品
I'd like you to see my new piece.
那是我莫大的荣幸
It would be an honor for me.
不  这才是我的荣耀
No, the honor would be all mine.
我相信
I believe....I believe...
这是有始以来最好的歌剧作品
it is the best opera yet written, my friends.
萨列里
Salieri!
你是音乐界最好的作曲家
You are the brightest star in the musical firmament.
维也纳与我向你致敬
You do honor to Vienna and to me.
莫扎特!
Herr Mozart!
-你来了我很高兴  -我怎么可能不来
-It was good of you to come. -How could I not?
你喜欢我的作品吗?
Did my work please you?
我从不知道有人能写出这种音乐
I never knew that music like that was possible.
-你只是在恭维我  -不  是真的
-You flatter me. -No, no.
当人们听到这音乐
One hears such sounds...
就会想到  萨列里
and what can one say but: Salieri!
每人在这里  我们来客人了  我们有酒!
Everybody's here, and we've got guests. Bravo! I've got some more.
你记得我的好朋友希克
You remember my good friend Schikaneder. Come in.
进来别害差
Don't be shy.
这位是个好女孩  这位也是
-This is a very nice girl, and this -Wolfie?
怎么了  亲爱的
Yes, my love?
波非  这而位是从沙德堡来的
-These gentlemen are from Salzburg. -Salzburg?
沙德堡!  我们正在说沙德堡!
We were just talking about Salzburg.
波非
Wolfie....
你父亲去逝了
Your father is dead.
可怕的鬼魂...
So rose the dreadful ghost...
出现在他下个作品
from his next and blackest opera.
舞台上站着的是死去的指挥官
There on the stage, stood the figure of a dead commander.
我知道...
I knew...
只有我了解...
only I understood...
那是他父亲的替身
that the horrifying apparition was Leopold...raised from the dead!
莫扎特其实是在召唤他的亲身父亲
Wolfgang had actually summoned up his own father...
在全世界面前表达一个做儿子的孝心!
to accuse his son before all the world!
看的
It was...
真是恐怖而美妙
terrifying and wonderful to watch.
于是...
And now...
疯狂就在我心中产生了
the madness began in me.
精神一分为二
The madness of a man splitting in half.
因为我的影响
Through my influence, I saw to it...
《唐乔望尼》只演了五场
Don Giovanni was played only five times in Vienna.
但我五场却都去了
But, in secret, I went to every one of those five.
以祟敬的心欣赏似乎只有我一人
Worshiping sound I alone seemed to hear.
在听他的音乐  在那儿我了解到
And as I stood there, understanding how...
他生气的父亲  虽然死了
that bitter old man was still possessing his poor son...
可是仍然支配着他
even from beyond the grave...
我开始有了计划
I began to see a way...
一个可怕的计划
a terrible way...
可以胜过上帝的计划!
I could finally triumph...over God.
莫扎特?
Herr Mozart?
我要请你作曲
I have come to commission work from you.
什么曲子?
-What work? -A Mass for the dead.
安魂曲!
What dead?
谁死了?
Who is dead?
一位应享有安魂曲而没得到的人
A man who deserved a Requiem Mass and never got one.
-你是谁?  -我只是个信差
-Who are you? -I am only a messenger.
你接受吗?
Do you accept?
报酬很好
You will be well paid.
你接受吗?
Do you accept?
尽快完成
Work fast.
不要对别人提起这事
And be sure tell no one what you do.
我会很快的再来看你
You will see me again soon.
我的计划很简单
My plan was so simple...
但却很吓人
that it terrified me.
首先我要拿到安魂曲  然后
First, I must get the death Mass, and then...
再完成莫扎特的死亡
I must achieve his death.
什么?
What?
他的葬礼!
His funeral!
想像一下
Imagine it!
在教堂  所有的维也纳人都在那里
The cathedral, all Vienna sitting there.
莫扎特小小的棺材躺在维也纳的中央
His coffin. Mozart's little coffin in the middle.
然后
And then...
一片沉寂中
in that silence...
音乐扬起
music.
神圣的音乐
A divine music...
超脱所有的一切
bursts out over them all.
伟大的死亡
A great Mass of death.
伟大的为莫扎特而作的安魂曲
Requiem Mass for Wolfgang Mozart.
由他生前最好的朋友...
Composed by his devoted friend...
萨列里写的
Antonio Salieri.
在音乐中那么庄严
What sublimity!
那么气派
What depth!
那么热情
What passion in the music!
萨列里终于受到神的付托
Salieri has been touched by God at last...
上帝也被迫要听萨列里的
and God forced to listen!
也无法阻止萨列里
Powerless to stop it!
我终于也反过来笑他了
I, for once, in the end, laughing at him!
使我担心的  是如何实际杀人
The only thing that worried me was the actual killing.
我怎么作的呢?
How does one do that?
人们如何能杀人呢?
How does one kill a man?
梦想...
It's one thing...
是一回事
to dream about it.
实际作的时候...
Very different when you....
非常不一样了
When you have to do it...
用自己的一双手
with your own hands.
请进
Come in!
我来吃晚餐
I've come to dinner
晚餐?  你疯了是不是  我是贵族
Dinner! Are you mad? I'm a nobleman!
我只和与我同高的人吃饭
I only ever dine with people of my own height!
停下
Stop it!
当心  当心
Be careful Be careful
抓紧
Hold tight
我是著名的...
I'm a famous...
骑手
horseman
我们是有名的马
And we're a famous horsy
踢我一脚  亲爱的
Give me a hoof, my darling
而我会给你我的心
And I'll give you my heart
把我带到你的马厩
Take me to your stable
我们永远也不会分开
And nevermore we'll part
杀了我  杀了我
Kill me Kill me
我们将进入女高音的部分
We're going to make a soprano stew
And when you make a soprano stew
闭嘴!
Shut up!
那样的曲调会让我死亡
I'm sick to death of that tune!
给我一些干草  我的亲爱的
Give me some hay, my darling
而我将给你我的心
And I'll give you my heart
干草!  干草!
Leporello! Some hay!
我希望...
We hope...
你能得到满足
you're contented
伴随着...
With what...
我们的演出
we've presented
喜欢我们的和平鸽
And love our dove of peace
喜欢...
And love...
我们的和平鸽
our dove of peace
-你觉得如何?  -好极了
-What did you think? -It was wonderful!
-他喜欢那些朱儒  -很有趣
-He liked the little people. -It's all in good fun.
我喜欢马
I liked the horse.
如果你在这里演《唐乔望尼》
I tell you, if you played Don Giovanni here...
你必会大获成功
you would've had a wonderful success.
你属于这里
You belong here.
不是属于虚伪的宫廷  你可以做你想做的任何事
Not at the snobby court. You could do anything you like.
愈荒唐愈好  那才是人们要的  想像力
The more fantastic, the better. That's what people want: fantasy.
你应替我写个适当的角巴
You write a proper part for me...
几首感人的歌
a couple of catchy songs...
我保证你一定成功
I guarantee you a triumph deluxe!
-你怎么认为?  -你要付我们多少钱
-What do you say? -How much will you pay him?
啊!
Ah!
你带着你的经纪人
Well! I see you brought your manager with you.
太太
Well, madame...
全部收入的一半如何
how about half the receipts?
收入的一半!
Half the receipts!
太太!  我是指现付!
-Stanzi! -I'm talking about now.
要现付多少定金
How much will you pay him now? Down payment.
定金!
Down payment?
你以为我是谁?  皇帝?
Who do you think I am, the emperor?
我该走了
Whoops. I have to go.
好好欣赏下一段
Stay here, you'll enjoy this next one.
你不会接受吧!
You won't do this.
-为什么不  全部收入的一半  -什么时候?
-Why not? Half the house! -When?
我们现在就需要钱  不是付定金就是不作
We need money now! He pays you now, or you don't do it.
我不信任他
I don't trust that man.
也不喜欢他处理你歌剧的方式太通俗
I don't like what he did with your opera. It was common.
不过你喜欢吧  小伙子
You liked it. Monkey, punky, flunky!
收入的一半!
Half the house.
你一毛也拿不到!  我要现在拿到手!
You'll never see a penny. I want it here in my hand.
-好呀!  在这儿  -闭嘴
-I'll put it here in your hand. -Shut up!
没有钱休想碰我
You won't put a thing in my hand until I see some money!
真是令人为难  你能想像有谁能为他做事吗?
It's embarrassing. Can't you think of anyone who can do something for him?
我想莫扎特可能是最后一个
I'm afraid Mozart is a lost cause, baron.
他在维也纳取得了巨大成功
He has succeeded in alienating practically the whole of Vienna.
他从未还钱
He never pays his debts.
我想像不出我能把他推荐给谁
I can't think of anyone to whom I'd dare recommend him.
莫扎特  真是奇怪!
Herr Mozart. What a surprise!
有什么能帮你吗?
What can I do for you?
我的学生对学习音乐依然感兴趣吗?
Is my pupil still interested in learning the art of music?
你的学生已经结婚住在很远的地方  年轻人
Your pupil is married and living in Mannheim, young man.
真的吗?
Really?
或许你的亲爱的老婆想学习呢?
Perhaps your dear wife might care to profit from my instruction.
怎么了?  莫扎特?
What is it, Mozart?
你怎么了?
What's the matter with you?
既然这表明没人想请我
Well ...since it appears no one is eager to hire my services...
您能帮忙借点钱给我吗?
could you favor me with a little money instead?
用来做什么用?
What for?
一个男人赚不到钱  就得去向别人借
If a man cannot earn, he must borrow.
那样很难
That's hardly the way to go about it.
你说得对
You are right, sir. You are right.
你也知道  我才华洋溢  你很富有
But you see, I am endowed with talent, and you with money.
如果我给我的...
If I offer mine...
你就得把你的给我
you should offer yours.
对不起  不行
I'm sorry, no.
求求你
Please.
我的回答是不  莫扎特
My answer is no, Mozart.
拜托!  拜托!
Please.
莫扎特!  莫扎特!
Please!
别理他
Don't answer it.
为何?
Why?
告诉他...
Tell him....
告诉他我不在
Tell him I'm not here.
告诉他...
Tell him....
说我正在工作
Tell him I'm working on it.
稍后回来
Come back later.
-抱歉  打扰你了吗?  -不
Am I interrupting?  No.
我的朋友呢?
Good. Where's our friend?
不在这里
He's not here.
他说他正在继续作曲中
But he's working on it, he told me to tell you.
那些吗?
Is that it?
他满意吗?
Is he happy with it?
这是什么?  安魂曲
What's this? A Requiem Mass?
-认为我是在参加葬礼  -放下
-You think I'm in the funeral business? -Leave that alone!
-放下  那不是给你的  -对不起
-Put it down! It's not for you! -I'm sorry.
我要你替我作的曲你写了没有
What have you got for me?
完成了吗?
Finished?
-什么?  -The vaudeville  你认为是什么?
What? -The vaudeville, what do you think?
是的!
Yes.
-我能看看吗?  -不能!
-Can I see it? -No.
为什么不能?
Why not?
因为没有什么可看
Because there's nothing to see.
听着
Look...
你说下礼拜可排演的
I asked you if we could start rehearsals next week and you said yes.
可以呀!  在那儿?  让我看看
-Well, we can. -So let me see it. Where is it?
这
Here.
全在我脑子里  剩下的只要把他写下来
It's all right here in my noodle. The rest is just scribbling.
喝酒及把它写下来  喝酒及把它写下来
Scribbling and bibbling. Bibbling and scribbling.
-你想喝点东西吗?  -你这小子
-Like a drink? -Look, you little clown!
你知道我雇了多少人
Do you know how many people I've hired?
-放开他  -我要付钱给人家!
-Leave him alone! -I'm paying them!
-他已尽他的全力了  -我付钱而却来等你写完曲子  真荒谬
-He's doing his best. -Paying them to wait. It's ridiculous!
你知道什么叫荒谬吗?  你的剧本
You know what's ridiculous? Your libretto!
是吗?
Oh!
只有白痴才会要这种剧本
Only an idiot would ask him to work on that!
弄蛇的摩笆
Twelve-foot snakes, magic flutes?
那么写安魂曲又有多高明
What's so intelligent about a Requiem?
钱!  钱!
Money. Money.
疯了!
You're mad.
显然她也疯了
She's mad.
写下来  兄弟!  把你的灵感写下
-Oh, yes? -Wolfie, write it down.
写下来
Just write it down.
写在纸上
On paper.
在你的脑中根本没有用
It's no use to anybody in your head.
去你的  安魂曲
To hell with your death Mass!
冷静!  你是怎么了
Calm yourself. What's the matter with you?
-我不再到那儿工作了  -为什么?  发生什么事?
-I won't work there anymore. -What happened?
你不知道是怎么一回事
You don't know what it's like.
莫扎特令我害怕
Herr Mozart frightens me.
他整天喝酒
He drinks all day...
并且吃药  使他变得更糟
then takes all that medicine and it makes him worse.
他有没有在工作?
Is he working?
我好怕  真的!
Oh, I am frightened, sir, really!
-当他讲话时  根本就是胡言乱语  -他有没有在工作?
-When he speaks, he makes no sense. -Is he working?
我想有吧!
I suppose so.
他常坐下来写什么歌剧的
He sits there all the time, doing some silly opera.
-歌剧?  -求求你别再叫我回去
-Opera? -Don't ask me to go back again.
我好怕!  我真的好怕
I'm frightened. I'm very, very frightened!
你确定是歌剧吗?
Are you sure it's an opera?
我还没有作完
I don't have it yet.
你答应了我的要求了吗?
Are you neglecting my request?
不..哦...
No. No, I....
我答应过你
I promise you...
要给你写一个好歌剧的
I'll give you a wonderful piece, the best I ever
这是我太太
This is my wife, Stanzi.
我已工作了一整夜  对吗?
I've been sick, but I'm all right now, aren't I?
是的  没错
Yes, sir. He's all right.
而他也很辛苦的在工作
And he's working on it very hard.
我还需要两个星期  求求你
Give me two more weeks. Please.
我会尽力完成它的  我保证!
The sooner you finish, the greater your reward.
去完成把
Work.
莫扎特
Wolfie.
我想你是真的发疯了
I think you really are going mad.
你替那白痴演员作得像个下奴  而他却分文末付
You slave for that idiot actor who won't give you a penny!
而这个人  他不是个鬼
And here, this is not a ghost!
他是个活生生的人且付你钱
This is a real man, who puts down real money.
你为何不完成它呢?
Why on earth won't you finish it?
你能给我个我能了解的理由吗?
Can you give me one reason I can understand?
他这么作是在杀我
It's killing me.
你醉了!  对不对?
You're drunk, aren't you?
萝拉说你一直在喝酒
Be honest, tell me. You've been drinking.
太不公平了  我一天到晚都在担心你
It's not fair. I worry about you all the time.
尽一切力量来帮助你
I do everything I can to help you.
而你却只会喝酒  胡言乱语  和吓我
And all you do is drink and talk nonsense and frighten me.
你回床上去吧!
Go back to bed!
求你了
Please.
我宁可坐在此
Let me.... Let me sit here.
跟你坐在此
Let me stay here with you.
我作的  我为此感到骄做
I did it. And I was proud to do it.
我告诉她说  走吧!  带着孩子一道走吧!
"Leave!" I said. "Right away. Take the child with you!
这儿有钱去那间修养所去  寻回你的健康吧!  令人吃惊
Go to the spa and get your health back." I was shocked.
令人吃惊当看到她变成那种模样
Shocked to my foundation when I saw her.
可怜的孩子我不敢相信我的眼睛
I couldn't believe my eyes, poor little thing.
你这个魔鬼  没人比得上你  是不是
You monster! No one exists but you, do they?
你和你的音乐  我警告过她
You and your music. I warned her.
选个男子汉  不要选个小孩
"Choose a man, not a baby," I said.
如她嫁给你  一生不幸  你这自私的东西
"You marry him, you won't have a pot to piss in." You selfish thing!
你这自私的东西你听见了吗?
Selfish, that's what you are. Simply selfish! Do you hear me?
扶他起来
Pick him up.
把他扶起来
Pick him up!
小心  过来帮忙!
Be careful. Come with me.
你跟我来
You, follow me.
结束了吗?  结束了
-Is it over? -Yes, it's over. It's over.
走!
Go!
走吧!  走!  走!
Go, go. go.
走!  走!
Go! Go!
你太太呢?
Where is your wife?
她身体不好  去休养处了
She's not well either. She went to the spa.
你对我真好
You are so good to me.
我非常感谢你
Truly. Thank you.
不要!  请你不要挂意
Please!
真高兴你来看我的歌剧
No, I mean to come to my opera.
你  你是唯一来的我的朋友
You. You are the only colleague of mine who came.
莫扎特
Mozart.
我从不错过你写的任何作品
I would never miss anything you had written.
-都是些小儿科  -不  不!
-It's just a vaudeville. -No, no!
超绝的作品
It's a sublime piece.
祟高的作品
The grandest operone!
我告诉你
I tell you...
你是我所知的最伟大的作曲家
you are the greatest composer known to me.
真的?
Do you mean it?
是他!  是谁?
-It's him! -Who?
那个人
The man.
他来了
He's here.
叫他走开!
Tell him to go away.
告诉他我有事别让他进来
Tell him I'm still working on it. Don't let him in.
不  等等!
No, no. Wait!
问问他现在能给我一些钱吗?
Ask him if he would give me some money now.
告诉他  如果他给  我就会帮他完成
Tell him if he would, it will help me to finish it.
萨列里!  是的
-Salieri? -Yes.
-他在吗?  -他在睡觉
-Can we come in? -Better not. He's sleeping.
我知道他晕倒了  他还好吗?
-He's all right, though? -Yes, he's just exhausted.
是的他只是太累了  头昏昏的
He became dizzy, that's all.
-告诉他我们来过好吗?  -好的
-Well, tell him we came by, won't you? -Of course.
给他这个  他的报酬
Give him this. That's his share.
这会使他高兴  当然!
-That should cheer him up. -Indeed!
各位晚安!  真的是...
And now, good night to you all. It was...
...完美之作
perfection, truly.
怎么样?
Thank you.
怎么回事?
What happened?
他说给你这个
He said to give you this.
如果你明晚之前能完成
And if you finish by tomorrow night...
它将会付你另外100元
he will pay you another hundred ducats.
另外的...?
Another...?
那太赶了  明天晚上!
That's too soon. Tomorrow night....
不可能!
It's impossible.
-他说1OO元?  -是的
-Did he say a hundred? -Yes.
太赶了!
It's too soon.
我能否...
Can I...?
我能帮你忙吗?
Could I help you?
你会吗?
Would you?
事实上你能的
Actually, you could.
我要走!  去哪儿
-I want to go. -Where?
-我要回去维也那!  -现在?
-I want to go back to Vienna.  Now?
-是的!  -为什么?
Yes. Why?
我觉得不对
I feel wrong.
我觉得在这里不大对
I feel wrong being here.
在什么地方停了  在Recordare(乐曲章节名)的结尾
-Where did I stop? -The end of the Recordare.
下面是Confutatis(乐曲章节名)...
So now Confutatis....
你怎么翻译这一段歌词
How would you translate that?
付诸地狱之火
"Consigned to flames of woe."
-你相信这种说法吗?  -什么?
-Do you believe in it? -What?
火永不灭  永远燃烧着你
A fire which never dies, burning you forever.
恩
Oh, yes.
也许吧
Possible.
-来吧  让我们开始继续作曲  -我们在降F大调停止
-Come, let's begin. -We ended in F major.
接着  降A小调
-Yes. -So, now, A minor.
-A小调!  -是的
-A minor. -Yes.
Confutatis(乐曲章节名)部分  A小调
Confutatis. A minor.
开始声乐部分
Start with the voices.
-由男低音开始  进入第二节  -时间是?
-Basses first. Second beat of the -Time?
通常的时间  第一节第二拍的时候
Common time. Second beat of the first measure.
在A小调
On A.
第二节第二拍
Second measure, second beat.
你知道吗?
You see?
-G调?  -当然
-Yes. G-sharp? -Of course.
再来第三节第二拍  E调
Second beat of the third measure, on E.
记下来了吗?  给我看看
Do you have me? Show me.
很好  很好
Good. Good.
现在男高音部分
Now the tenors.
第一小节第四拍  C调
Fourth beat of the first measure, on C.
第二节第四拍  D调
Second measure, fourth beat. D.
-好了没?  -好了  继续
-All right? -Yes, continue.
第四节第二拍  F调
Second beat of the fourth measure, on F.
现在弦乐部分  第二低音管和长号  男低音
Now the orchestra. Second bassoon, bass trombones, basses.
三者全部使用相同音符及节拍
Identical notes and rhythm.
第一低音管及高音乐器  与男高音同调
First bassoon, tenor trombones, with the tenors.
-太快了  太快了  -你记下了没
-You go too fast. -Do you have it?
-第一低音管及高音乐器是怎样?  -同男高音
-Bassoon to trombone what? -With the tenors.
-全都相同音符吗?  -当然  乐器来加强声乐
-Identical? -The instruments doubling the voices.
小号和鼓  小号在D调  听我说
Trumpets and timpani. Trumpets in D. Listen.
-我不明白  -听我的
-I don't understand! -Listen!
小号用D音  起主导作用的主音  第一拍和第三拍
Trumpets in D, tonic and dominant, first and third beats.
全部和音!
It goes with the harmony
对
Yes. Yes, yes!
我明白了  完了吗?
I understand. And that's all?
真的火还没形容到呢!
No, now for the real fire. Strings in unison.
重复音部分进入  像这样
Ostinato, on A. Like this:
第一大调上升
Next measure is rising.
-跟上没有  给我看看  -跟的上  跟的上
-Do you have it? Show me. -Yes, yes.
太美了是  继续
-It's wonderful! -Yes, yes. Go on.
轻声
Sotto voce.
-写下来  -好的  好的
-Write that down! -Yes, yes.
-最弱音  -最弱音
-Pianissimo. -Pianissimo?
C大调
C major.
女高音女低音第三线  女低音用C音
Sopranos and altos in thirds. Altos on C, sopranos above.
-女高音在第二段用F音?  -是的
-Sopranos up to F on the second voca? -Yes.
然后再倒回去  在下面  仅仅小提琴  琶音
And on dictus. And underneath, just violins. Arpeggios.
然后缩减八分音符到固定音型
Scale in eighth notes, then back to ostinato.
-记下了没?  -太快了  拜托你  等等
-Do you have it? -You go too fast.
-记下了没?  -等等
-Do you have it? -One moment, please!
好了
Yes.
让我看全部谱曲
Good. Show me the whole thing from the beginning.
你要休息一下吗?
Do you want to rest a bit?
不  我一点也不累
No, I'm not tired at all.
我们停一下
We'll stop for a moment.
-然后完成最后一段  -我能继续作  我保证我不累
-Then we'll finish the Lacrimosa. -I can keep going. I assure you.
你能陪在这  让我休息一下吗
Will you stay with me while I sleep a little?
我不会离开你的
I'm not leaving you.
-好惭愧!
I'm so ashamed.
-惭愧什么?
Of what?
我好傻!
I was foolish.
我以为你不在乎我的作品或是我个人
I thought you did not care for my work, or me.
原谅我
Forgive me.
你在这里干什么?
What are you doing here?
你的丈夫 他病了
Your husband took sick.
我带他回来
I brought him home.
为何是你?
Why you?
因为我就在旁边
Because, madame, I was at hand.
非常感谢  你现在可以走了
Well, thank you very much. You can go now.
他需要我  太太
He needs me, ma'am.
不  他不需要
No, he doesn't.
我不许你在这里  请你走吧!
And I don't want you here. Just go, please.
-他叫我留下  -我叫你
-He asked me to stay. -And I'm ask
莫扎特
Wolfie?
莫扎特!
我回来了
I'm back.
我多么想念你
I missed you so much.
只要你
If you'd just...
表示需要我
show me that you need me.
我也会尽力作好你的妻子
And I'll try to do better too.
这是什么?
What is this?
不  不是这些 不是这些
No, Wolfie, not this. Not this.
你再也不会想像现在这样工作了
You're not to work on this ever again.
我已经决定了
I've decided.
这不是他的笔迹
This is not his handwriting.
那是我的
It's mine.
我帮他写下
I was assisting him.
他不再写这些了
He's not to work on this anymore.
是这些导致他生病
-It's making him ill. -But
晚安
Good night.
很抱歉没有仆人送你出去
I regret we have no servants to show you out, Herr Salieri.
请见谅!  并请你回去
Please respect my wish and go.
夫人
Madame...
我要尊重你先生的意思
I will respect his.
莫扎特
Wolfie.
莫扎特?
Wolfie?
莫扎特!  莫扎特!
Wolfie! Wolfie!
你慈悲的上帝
Your merciful God.
他毁掉他最爱的人  而不愿让那些平庸的人...
He destroyed his own beloved, rather than let a mediocrity...
分享他荣耀中的一小点
share in the smallest part of his glory.
他杀了莫扎特
He killed Mozart.
却让我活在世上忍受折磨
And kept me alive to torture.
32年的折磨
Thirty-two years of torture.
32年  我慢慢在发现我自己成为老人
Thirty-two years of slowly watching myself become extinct.
我作的音乐
My music...
逐渐为人淡忘
growing fainter.
越来越被世人遗忘
All the time fainter...
再也没人演奏了
till no one plays it at all.
而他的
And his....
早安!  大师  该刷洗了
Good morning, professor. Time for the water closet.
我们准备了你最爱吃的早餐
Then we have your favorite breakfast. Sugar rolls. He loves those.
可口的糖豆
Fresh sugar rolls.
我会为你申言  神父
I will speak for you, Father.
我为全天下的平庸的人申言
I speak for all mediocrities in the world.
我是他们的斗士
I am their champion.
我是他们的保护神
I am their patron saint.
平庸的人到处都是
Mediocrities everywhere...
我宣布赦免你
I absolve you.
我宣布赦免你们所有人
I absolve you all.